A Finding Aid to the Ben Shahn Papers, 1879-1990, bulk 1933-1970, in the Archives of American Art AAA.shahben
Archives of American Art
- Printed Material, 1912-1988; Series 8; 3.22 Linear feet Boxes 30-33, 35, OV 39
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, circa 1930s-circa 1960s (Box 31, Folder 43)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, circa 1950s-circa 1960s (Box 31, Folder 44)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1932-1934 (Box 31, Folder 45)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, circa 1938 (Box 31, Folder 46)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs for Shahn, circa 1944-1947 (Box 31, Folder 47)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1951-1952 (Box 31, Folder 48)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1955 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1956-1957 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1958 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, circa 1959-1960s (Box 32, Folder 4)
    disbound unidentified catalog of reproductions
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1959 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1961 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1962 (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1963 (Box 32, Folder 8)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1964-1966 (Box 32, Folder 9)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1967 (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1968 (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1969 (Box 32, Folder 12)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1970 (Box 32, Folder 13)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1971-1979 (Box 32, Folder 14)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1981 (Box 32, Folder 15)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Others, circa 1950s-circa 1960s; 2 Folders (Box 32, Folder 16-17)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Others, 1952-1956 (Box 32, Folder 18)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Others, 1957 (Box 32, Folder 19)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Others, 1958-1959 (Box 32, Folder 20)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Others, 1960-1961 (Box 32, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Others, 1962; 4 Folders (Box 32, Folder 22-25)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Others, 1963; 4 Folders (Box 32, Folder 26-29)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Others, 1964; 2 Folders (Box 32, Folder 30-31)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Others, 1965 (Box 32, Folder 32)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Others, 1966 (Box 32, Folder 33)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Others, 1967 (Box 32, Folder 34)
  - Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Others, 1984, 1988 (Box 32, Folder 35)
  - Pamphlets Concerning Farmers, 1935-1936 (Box 32, Folder 36)
  - Pamphlets Concerning Unions, 1934-1937; 2 Folders (Box 32, Folder 37-38)
  - Pamphlets, Miscellaneous, 1912-1944; 2 Folders (Box 32, Folder 39-40)
  - Pamphlets, Miscellaneous, 1946-1967; 4 Folders (Box 33, Folder 1-4)
  - Picture Postcards, undated (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Printed Travel Souvenirs, circa 1950s-circa 1960s (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - Programs, circa 1951-1964 (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Prospectuses, 1957-1966 (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Publications Illustrated by Shahn, 1949 (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - Publications Illustrated by Shahn, circa 1950s-circa 1960s (Box 33, Folder 10)
  - Publications Illustrated by Shahn, 1952-1956 (Box 33, Folder 11)
  - Publications Illustrated by Shahn, 1957-1958 (Box 33, Folder 12)
  - Publications Illustrated by Shahn, 1959 (Box 33, Folder 13)
  - Publications Illustrated by Shahn, 1964-1967 (Box 33, Folder 14)
  - Publications Illustrated by Others, 1962-1964 (Box 33, Folder 15)
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Shahn, 1953-1966; 3 Folders (Box 33, Folder 16-18)
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Others, undated; 2 Folders (Box 33, Folder 19-20)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1950s-circa 1960s (Box 33, Folder 21)
  - Oversized Material from Art Front Magazine, 1934-1935 (Box 35)
    oversized material scanned with Box 30, F45
  - Oversized Material from Publications Illustrated by Shahn, 1959 (Box 35)
    oversized material scanned with Box 33, F13
  - Oversized Material from Brochures for Events, circa 1950s-circa 1960s (Box OV 39)
    oversized material scanned with Box 30, F51
  - Oversized Material from Brochures for Events, 1965-1972 (Box OV 39)
    oversized material scanned with Box 30, F54
  - Oversized Material from Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Shahn, 1963 (Box OV 39)
    oversized material scanned with Box 32, F8
  - Oversized Material from Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Others, 1952-1956 (Box OV 39)
    oversized material scanned with Box 32, F18
  - Oversized Material from Exhibition Announcements, Catalogs, Others, 1966 (Box OV 39)
    oversized material scanned with Box 32, F33
  - Oversized Material from Reproductions of Artwork by Shahn, 1953-1966 (Box OV 39)
    oversized material scanned with Box 33, F17
  - Oversized Material from Clippings, 1936-1945 (Box OV 40)
    oversized material scanned with Box 31, F7
- Photographs, circa 1900-1969; Series 9; 0.86 Linear feet Boxes 33-35
  Photographs are of Shahn and family members, friends and colleagues in addition to photographs taken by Shahn. Found here are prints of photographs Shahn took in New York City in the early 1930s when his interest in photography was developing, as well as prints from some of his finest images taken for the FSA and the Resettlement Administration.
  Family photographs include pictures of Judith and Ezra Shahn as children and a young Susanna Shahn. Photos of friends and colleagues include a picture of Shahn and Alexander Calder at the Porta Portese in Rome, circa 1957, and a photo of Shahn with Palma Biccarelli (Director of the Modern Museum in Rome), Louisa Calder and Renato Gattuso, circa 1957. Other friends and colleagues pictured in this series include: Morris Cantor, William Cummings, Jack Eastman, Laura Eastman, Martha Graham, Bartlett Hayes, Helen Hayes, Senator Javits, Harry Knight, Loren Macivor, Joe Ormai (working on the Social Security Building mural, circa 1941), Amadee Ozanfant, Jerome Robbins, Nelson Rockefeller, Nate Saltenstall, Charles Sheeler, David Smith, James Thrall Soby, Monroe Wheeler, and William Zorach. There is also a photo of Shahn at Trianon Press in Paris, France, with M. Crompe Pochoiriete.
  Also found are photos of Shahn receiving Honorary Doctorates from Harvard and Princeton Universities and a medal from George Biddle.
  Photographs taken by Shahn of New York City in the 1930s include prints of photos used for his paintings Handball (1939) (see Box 34, Folder 6) and Blind Accordion Player (1945) (see Box 34, Folder 10).
  FSA photographs taken by Shahn of North Carolina (box 33, folder 33) are of children musicians used as the source for his painting, Song (1950.)
  Photographs taken by others include a mounted print inscribed on the back: "Hello Ben, Dorothea Lange. Made in St. George, Utah, 1956"; a photograph by Walker Evans, circa 1929, and two FSA photos taken by Russell Lee and Arthur Rothstein.
  This series has been scanned in entirety, with the exception of photographic negatives.
  - Shahn, Family, Friends and Colleagues (Box 33)
    - Family Photographs, circa 1900, circa 1940-circa 1950s (Box 33, Folder 22)
    - Shahn House in Truro, MA, 1955 (Box 33, Folder 23)
    - Ben and Bernarda Shahn, circa 1950s (Box 33, Folder 24)
    - Ben and Bernarda Shahn in Italy, 1956 (Box 33, Folder 25)
    - Shahn with Friends and Colleagues, circa 1934-circa 1960s (Box 33, Folder 26)
    - Shahn with Friends and Colleagues in Italy, circa 1957-1958 (Box 33, Folder 27)
    - Shahn Receiving Honors and Awards, circa 1960s (Box 33, Folder 28)
    - Friends and Colleagues, circa 1946-circa 1965 (Box 33, Folder 29)
  - Photographs Taken by Shahn (Box 33)
    - FSA Photos of Alabama, 1937 (Box 33, Folder 30)
    - FSA Photos of Arkansas, 1935 (Box 33, Folder 31)
    - FSA Photos of Louisiana, 1935 (Box 33, Folder 32)
    - FSA Photos of North Carolina, 1937 (Box 33, Folder 33)
    - FSA Photos of Ohio, 1938; 4 Folders (Box 33, Folder 34-37)
      includes contact sheets
    - FSA Photos of Tennessee, 1935-circa 1938 (Box 33, Folder 38)
    - Japan, circa 1960 (Box 33, Folder 39)
      contact sheet
    - Jersey Homesteads, Fourth of July Celebration, circa 1940 (Box 33, Folder 40)
    - Jersey Homesteads, Nursery School Children, circa 1940; 5 Folders (Box 33, Folder 41-45)
    - New York City, 1932-1936; 11 Folders (Box 34, Folder 1-11)
      (folders 6 and 10 include photos used for Handball and Blind Accordion Player)
    - New York City, San Gennaro Festival, circa 1950 (Box 34, Folder 12)
    - Progressive Party Rally (possibly taken by Shahn), circa 1949 (Box 34, Folder 13)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Shahn (Box 34)
    - General, undated; 3 Folders (Box 34, Folder 14-16)
    - CIO Political Action Committee Publications, 1944; 3 Folders (Box 34, Folder 17-19)
    - War Information Posters, 1941-1944 (Box 34, Folder 20)
  - Shahn Exhibition Installations, 1958, 1963 (Box 34, Folder 21)
  - Photos Taken by Others, circa 1929, 1956 (Box 34, Folder 22)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Others, circa 1960-1969; 3 Folders (Box 34, Folder 23-25)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Others, War Information Posters, 1941-1944 (Box 34, Folder 26)
  - Oversized Material from New York City, 1932-1936 (Box 35)
    oversized material scanned with Box 34, F10
- Interview Transcripts, 1943-1968; Series 10; 0.25 Linear feet Box 34
  This series includes transcripts of 8 interviews of Shahn and panel discussions in which he participated. See Series 11: Audiovisual Material for the actual recordings of three of the interviews: Monitor: A Film About Ben Shahn's America, and interviews of Shahn by Arlene Francis from 1965 and 1968.
  Interviews are arranged chronologically. This series has been scanned in entirety.
  - "Living Art," CBS: Interview of Ben Shahn and Harry Strenberg by Morse, 1943 (Box 34, Folder 27)
  - "See It Now": Commentary on Senator Joseph McCarthy by Edward R. Murrow, 1954 March 9 (Box 34, Folder 28)
  - "Children of God" (interviews of children) by Tony Schwartz, circa 1955 (Box 34, Folder 29)
  - The Creative Mind #7, "The Painter as Creator": Interview of Ben Shahn by Nadya Aisenberg, introduction by Lyman Bryson, circa 1957 (Box 34, Folder 30)
  - Monitor: A Film About Ben Shahn's America, 1959 (Box 34, Folder 31)
  - The Open Mind, "Nostalgia for the 1930s": Panel discussion with Ben Shahn, Hamilton Fish, Benny Goodman, Raymond Moley, and A. H. Raskin, Moderator: Eric F. Goldman, 1962 February 4 (Box 34, Folder 32)
  - Personal Close-Up: Interview of Ben Shahn by Mike Wallace, 1964 (Box 34, Folder 33)
  - WCBS-TV: Interview of Ben Shahn by Jack, 1965 (Box 34, Folder 34)
  - WOR (radio): Interview of Ben Shahn by Arlene Francis, 1965 April 30 (Box 34, Folder 35)
  - WOR (radio): Interview of Ben Shahn by Arlene Francis, 1968 September 13 (Box 34, Folder 36)
- Audio and Video Recordings, 1959-1968; Series 11; 0.25 Linear feet Box 34
  This series consists of recordings of a BBC-TV film Monitor: A Film About Ben Shahn's America and 3 7" reel-to-reel recordings of two interviews of Shahn by Arlene Francis (see Series 10: Interview Transcripts for transcripts), and a 1963 recording, "Four Sound Stories from Tony Schwartz," (not transcribed).
  This series has not been digitized.
  - Monitor: A Film About Ben Shahn's America, BBC-TV, 16mm reel of motion picture film, 1959? (Box 34, Folder 37)
  - Monitor: A Film About Ben Shahn's America, BBC-TV (transferred 2003), 1 VHS videotape and 1 Digital Betacam tape, 1959; 2 Folders (Box 34, Folder 38-39)
  - "Four Sound Stories from Tony Schwartz," 7" reel-to-reel audio tape, untranscribed, 1963, November 22 (Box 34, Folder 40)
  - WOR (radio): Interview of Ben Shahn by Arlene Francis, 7" reel-to-reel audio tape, 1965 April 30 (Box 34, Folder 41)
  - WOR (radio): Interview of Ben Shahn by Arlene Francis, 7" reel-to-reel audio tape, 1968 September 13 (Box 34, Folder 42)
- Artifacts, circa 1930s-circa 1960s; Series 12; 2 Folders Box 34
  Only the first item in this series has been scanned.
  - One Sock, Printed with "Merry Christmas from the School of Visual Arts,", circa 1950s-circa 1960s (Box 34, Folder 43)
  - Pair of Shoelaces and 3 Tablets of Marezine, circa 1930s-circa 1960s (Box 34, Folder 44)